We're going to be doing דף ל"ה Daf Lamed Hei in the
בבלי. Bavli. We'll start with a very short section of the ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, or not super short, but anyway we'll start with the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. פרק ד' הלכה ו'. Perek Dalet Halacha Vav.
דיני ממונות גומרין בו ביום בין לזכות בין לחובה ודיני נפשות גומרין
בו ביום לזכות וביום שלאחריו לחובה לפיכך אין דנין לא בערב שבת
ולא בערב יום טוב. Dinei Mamonot gomrin bo bayom, bein lezechut bein
lechovah vedinei nefashot gomrin bo bayom lezechut, uveyom shelacharyo lechovah, lefichach ein
danin lo be'erev shabbat velo be'erev yom tov. Okay, so monetary cases
you can finish on the same day,
whereas capital crimes you have to at least do הלנת הדין, halanat
hadin, sleep on it, so you have to at least wait until
the next day to find the person guilty. And therefore you can't
start ערב שבת erev shabbat or ערב יום טוב erev yom tov
because you won't be able to continue on the immediate next day.
The question is why you can't wait a day and have the
finish the judgment on Sunday. The גמרא Gemara will discuss. Let's look
at the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. תני העד אינו מלמד לא זכות ולא חובה.
Tani, ha'ed eino melamed lo zechut velo chovah. So we saw this
already in the בבלי Bavli earlier. The witness himself cannot argue on
his own behalf to for the person's innocence or guilt. מנהלון, Minahalun,
where do you know this from? שנאמר ועד לא יענה בנפש למות.
Shene'emar ve'ed lo ya'aneh benefesh lamut. A person, a witness cannot answer
cannot respond against the person to put him to death, and reading
this now as not just about עדות edut but also about arguing
on the person's behalf. Now, that says that you can't do it
to argue to put him to death.
מנין שאף הוא אינו מלמד לא זכות ולא חובה? Minayin she'af hu
eino melamed lo zechut velo chovah?
So again, it's a query question about what this next line is.
The extra והוא, hu, does it mean that the defendant can't argue
for himself? But the defendant actually can argue for himself. We already
said the issue about זכות zechut and חובה. chovah. So the פני
משה Pnei Moshe says the first פסוק, pasuk, the first point showed
that he can't argue למות lamut to strengthen his testimony and to
put the guy to death. And now it's saying how do you
know that the witness can't argue in the guy's
defense? תלמוד לומר והוא לא יענה. Talmud lomar vehu lo ya'aneh. והוא
vehu again seems extra, so it seems it's to learn something with
the extra והוא hu here. Anyway, לא יענה בנפש למות. lo ya'aneh
benefesh lamut. Now what does that prove? So the way they explain
it, it's it's not you can't say to put the נפש nefesh
to death, but you can't לא יענה, lo ya'aneh, you can't have
any say בנפש למות benefesh lamut when it's an issue of someone's
death. You can't have any say whether to defend him or to
accuse or to strengthen the the argument of his guilt. ריש לקיש
אמר, Resh Lakish amar, and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says actually if
you argue on his behalf that is about a matter of death.
Why? דמים שאדם רואה את עצמו מזדמן. Damin she'adam ro'eh et atzmo
mizdamen. Sometimes you see yourself turning into an עד זומם, ed zomem,
ומפליג דבר שלא ימות. umaflig dvar shelo yamut. So then you try
to argue on the person's behalf because by if the person never
has the judgment passed against him, you won't become an עד זומם.
ed zomem. So this is the argument that we saw in the
בבלי Bavli that you're נוגע בעדות. nogea be'edut.
You're נוגע בעדות nogea be'edut to argue that he's committed the crime
because then you're strengthening your עדות, edut, and you're נוגע בעדות nogea
be'edut to say he's innocent because then you're protecting yourself against being
an עד זומם. ed zomem. Okay, now back to the point of
the משנה. Mishnah. מנין שצריכין שני ימים סמוכים זה לזה? Minayin shetzrichin
shenei yamim smuchin zeh lazeh? How do you know that you need
to be juxtaposed, you can't have a break of a day? So
before answering that question, I mean I mean how come you can't
do it ערב שבת. erev shabbat. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi is first going
to digress for a moment. רבי חזקיה ואחי בשם רבי אבהו אסור
לדון דיני ממונות בערב שבת. Rabbi Chizkiyahu va'achi beshem Rabbi Abbahu: Asur
ladun dinei mamonot be'erev shabbat. There's a teaching in the name of
רבי חזקיה Rabbi Chizkiyahu that you can't even judge monetary cases ערב
שבת, erev shabbat, presumably because it'll just get in the way of
your preparing for שבת. shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara says והדא מתניתא
פליגא, vehada matnita peliga, but our משנה Mishnah argues on this. לפיכך
אין דנין לא בערב שבת ולא בערב יום טוב דיני נפשות, Lefichach
ein danin lo be'erev shabbat velo be'erev yom tov dinei nefashot, that
capital crimes you can't do on ערב שבת, erev shabbat, הא דיני
ממונות דנין, ha dinei mamonot danim, but civil cases you can. So
the גמרא Gemara says ותני רבי חייא כן, vetani Rabbi Chiya ken,
and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya also teaches a ברייתא braita exactly that
way. דנין דיני ממונות בערב שבת ואין דנין דיני נפשות בערב שבת.
Danim dinei mamonot be'erev shabbat ve'ein danin dinei nefashot be'erev shabbat.
Monetary crimes can be on ערב שבת, erev shabbat, not capital crimes,
monetary cases. So how could you רבי חזקיה Rabbi Chizkiyahu say you
don't do monetary cases on ערב שבת? erev shabbat? אמר כאן להלכה
כאן למעשה. Amar kan lehalacha kan lema'aseh. One is theoretical, one is
practical, okay? Sometimes you'll have a תשובה teshuvah that will say להלכה
ולא למעשה. lehalacha velo lema'aseh. Theoretical debate of what the law should
be, but I'm not actually saying it as a practical ruling. So
theoretically להלכה lehalacha you can do monetary cases on ערב שבת. erev
shabbat. That's the דאורייתא d'Oraita הלכה. halacha.
But practically we don't do it on ערב שבת erev shabbat because
we want to give people time to prepare for שבת. shabbat. בדיעבד
Bediavad if you did do it, it still would be valid. Okay,
so now we go on. Okay. וידונוהו בערב שבת יגמר דינו בשבת.
Veyedunuhu be'erev shabbat yigmar dino beshabbat.
Now we're getting back to why not do דיני נפשות dinei nefashot
on ערב שבת. erev shabbat. Why not do it on ערב שבת
erev shabbat
and finalize the judgment on שבת? shabbat? ויהרגהו למוצאי שבת. Vehargehu lemotzaei
shabbat.
So we won't interrupt the deliberations, but we'll wait to actually execute
him until Sunday. No, אם אומר את כן נמצא דינו משתקע, im
omer at ken nimtza dino mishtake'ach, you are having the sun set
on his דין, din, it's עינוי דין. inui din. After you said
he is he is liable for the death penalty, you can't wait
till the next day to execute him.
ריש לקיש בעי וידונוהו... Resh Lakish ba'ei veyedunuhu... and finish the deliberations?
Now what's the argument to do it? ומאי אם עבודה דוחה שבת,
u-mai im avoda docha Shabbos, עבודה avoda overrides שבת. Shabbos. You do
עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ורציחת מצוה דוחה אותה,
u-retzichas mitzvah docha osa,
executing somebody, רציחת מצוה. retzichas mitzvah. It's very funny because the word
רציחה retzicha we normally say is murder which is a crime. You
should say maybe הריגת מצוה. harigas mitzvah. Very funny he uses that
phrase רציחה retzicha again, maybe that reflects the rabbi's, you know, anxiety
or whatever, you know, discomfort around execution. Anyway, but when so if
עבודה avoda overrides שבת, Shabbos, it's like the transitive axiom of inequality.
עבודה avoda is greater than שבת. Shabbos. Now executing somebody is greater
than עבודה. avoda. How do you know that? שנאמר מעם מזבחי תקחנו
למות. she-ne'emar me-im mizbechi tikachenu lamus. You have to take a כהן
Kohen away from the altar if he committed a capital crime to
execute him, even if that means that the עבודה avoda will not
take place. As תוספות Tosafos says in the בבלי, Bavli, even if
he's the only כהן Kohen to do the עבודה, avoda, you take
him away to execute him and you don't give primacy to the
עבודה. avoda. So here's the transitive axiom: עבודה avoda is greater than
שבת Shabbos because you do the עבודה avoda on שבת. Shabbos. Executing
is greater than the עבודה avoda because you'll execute somebody even if
it means that it interrupts the עבודה. avoda. So if executing is
greater than עבודה avoda and עבודה avoda is greater than שבת, Shabbos,
executing should be greater than שבת. Shabbos.
So שבת שעבודה דוחה אותה, Shabbos she-avoda docha osa, so if עבודה
avoda is greater than שבת Shabbos and pushes it off, אינו דין
שיהא רציחת מצוה דוחה אותה? eino din she-yei retzichas mitzvah docha osa?
So certainly executing should override שבת. Shabbos. So why not? רבי אילא
בשם רבי ינאי מכאן לבעלי דינים שלא ידמו. Rabbi Ila be-shem Rabbi
Yannai mikan le-ba'alei dinim she-lo yidamu. Here's the basis of how you
know you can't execute on שבת. Shabbos. בשבת מאי טעמא? be-Shabbos mai
ta'ama? Why? נאמר כאן בכל מושבותיכם ונאמר להלן והיו אלה לכם לחוקת
משפט לדורותיכם בכל מושבותיכם. ne'emar kan be-chol moshvoseichem ve-ne'emar le-hallan ve-hayu eileh
lachem le-chukas mishpat le-doroseichem be-chol moshvoseichem.
It says do not make a fire in all of your places
where you dwell and it says these shall be for the laws
of judgment in, you know, for generations בכל מושבותיכם be-chol moshvoseichem wherever
you dwell. And that's talking about executing murderers. מה להלן בבית דין
הכתוב מדבר אף כאן בבית דין הכתוב מדבר. mah le-hallan be-veis din
ha-kasuv medabber af kan be-veis din ha-kasuv medabber. In the same way
the second בכל מושבותיכם be-chol moshvoseichem is executing murderers, it's talking about
a בית דין. beis din.
When it says don't burn a fire, it's in the context of
executing for a בית דין. beis din. Don't do the punishment of
שריפה, sreifa, the execution of שריפה, sreifa, and don't do it on
שבת. Shabbos. The verse is explicit you don't execute on שבת Shabbos
even though you have a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. So you don't
execute on שבת Shabbos and presumably without explaining why the גמרא Gemara
asked and never answered, why don't we just take a pause? Deliberations
on Friday, continue the deliberations on Sunday. It's not עינוי הדין inuy
ha-din because you haven't ruled yet that the guy is liable, maybe
he's going to come off innocent, and then you'll execute him on
Monday. So it didn't answer that question why you can't take a
break in the deliberations, but assuming you can't, then you can't have
the גמר דין gmar din on שבת Shabbos and execute the next
day because that's הלנת הדין halanas ha-din and you can't execute on
שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so that's what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says is the
basis for not doing it on ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. Okay, we
now turn to the בבלי, Bavli, ל"ה. lamed heh. We pick up
at the very bottom of ל"ד עמוד ב'. lamed dalet amud beis.
And here we go. דיני נפשות דנים ביום. dinei nefashos danin ba-yom.
So capital crimes are only in the day. We learned that monetary
cases can start in the day and end at night. מנא הני
מילי, mena hanei millei, where do you know that capital crimes have
to everything be in the day, even the end of it has
to be in the day? אמר רב שימי בר חייא אמר קרא
והוקע אותם לה' נגד השמש. amar Rav Shimi bar Chiyya amar kra
ve-hoka osam la-Hashem neged ha-shemesh. This is about the people that sinned
for בעל פעור Baal Peor and it says and you shall sort
of suspend them, you know, hang them to God opposite the sun.
So you're hanging them, it's the גמר דין gmar din of דיני
נפשות dinei nefashos and it's נגד השמש, neged ha-shemesh, it's opposite the
sun in the day. So not only does the תחילת דין techilas
din have to be in the day, the גמר דין gmar din
has to be in the day as well. אמר רב חסדא מניין
להוקעה שהיא תלייה? amar Rav Chisda minayin le-hoka'ah she-hi tliyah? How do
you know that this means to suspend them, to hang them and
that's what you do after, you know, you
execute? דכתיב והוקענום לה' בגבעת שאול בחיר ה'. de-chsiv ve-hoka'anum la-Hashem be-Givas
Shaul bechir Hashem. This is talking about the, you know, גבעונים Givonim
when they there was a famine and it was because of what
שאול'ס Shaul's family had done to the גבעונים Givonim and the גבעונים
Givonim demanded that seven of שאול'ס Shaul's sons be executed and and
and hung. Okay, so it says that they were hung or they
were suspended in גבעת שאול. Givas Shaul. וכתיב u-chsiv and the verse
says
ותקח רצפה בת איה את השק ותטהו לה אל הצור va-tikach Ritzpa
bas Ayah es ha-sak va-tatohu lah el ha-tzur מתחילת קציר. mi-techilas katzir.
She basically used this sackcloth to cover them up, but it means
that they were exposed and they were exposed for everybody to see.
And
therefore anyway you see that the word הוקעה hoka'ah means to sort
of like to, you know, hang them and to suspend them. Okay,
now וכתיב ויאמר ה' אל משה, u-chsiv va-yomer Hashem el Moshe, now
since we've learned this פסוק, pasuk, these פסוקים, pesukim, we're going to
just interpret it. God said to משה, Moshe, קח את כל ראשי
העם kach es kol rashei ha-am and it says והוקע אותם לה'
נגד השמש. ve-hoka osam la-Hashem neged ha-shemesh. Like the פסוק pasuk is
a funny פסוק, pasuk, it says take all the heads of the
tribes and then, you know, hang them in front of God. And
then it says משה Moshe spoke to the heads, to the ראשי,
rashei, to, you know, to the ראשים rashim and said. judge all
the people. So were the heads being executed or were they judging?
So what do you, how do you interpret it? אם העם חטאו,
ראשי העם לקו. Im haam chatu, rashei haam laku. So the people
sinned but what did the, how did the leaders sin? Of course,
the leaders could have sinned because they let the people sin, because
they didn't educate the people better. But anyway, the point is, why
are you, why does the simple sense of the verse sound like
you're going to execute the leaders? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, Amar
lei hakadosh baruch hu l'Moshe, חלוק להם בתי דינין. Chalok lahem batei
dinin. No, no, no, speak to the leaders and not hang the
leaders. Speak to the leaders, create a lot of courts and have
the leaders judge the people and have והוקע אותם, ve-hoka otam, have
the leaders hang the guilty people. Okay, מאי טעמא? Mai taama? Now,
why do you have to have many courts? Why can't you all
do it in one big court? אילימא משום שאין דנין שניים ביום
אחד, Ilima mishum she-ein danin shnayim b'yom echad, you don't judge two
cases at the same capital crimes on the same day. ואמר רב
חסדא, Va-amar Rav Chisda, לא שנו אלא בשתי מיתות, lo shanu ela
b'shtei mitot, that's only if there're two separate death penalties and two
separate crimes. אבל במיתה אחת דנין, Aval b'mita achat danin, if it's
one death penalty and the exact same crime, you can hear multiple
cases in the same day. So why did they have to have
multiple courts? You know, just have one big court. אלא כדי שישוב
חרון אף השם מישראל, Ela k'dei she-yashuv charon af Hashem m'Yisrael, the
end of the verse says God's anger will turn away. He'll see
you setting up all these courts, you're trying to impose order, you're
dealing with defending God's honor and that will help abate God's anger.
Okay, anyway, from all of that we learn that the גמר דין
gmar din is also ביום. bayom. Now, דיני ממונות גומרין ביום. Dinei
mamonot gomrin bayom. Now the issue about whether you have to, can
finish it on the same day. Monetary cases you can finish it
on the same day. Capital cases you can finish it on the
same day for innocence, but for guilt you have to sleep on
it and wait until the next day. We saw even earlier, even
if you came up with a new argument for guilt and the
vote didn't change, you have to sleep on it another day. מנא
הני מילי? Mena hani mili? Where do you know this from? אמר
רבי חנינא דאמר קרא, Amar Rabbi Chanina d'amar kra, מלאתי משפט. meleiti
mishpat. This is of course about Yeshayahu bemoaning the perversion of the
justice in Israel and in Jerusalem. I was, I used to be
filled with justice, צדק ילין בה, tzedek yalin bah, righteousness slept in
the city, ועתה מרצחים, ve-ata meratzchim, and now murderers sleep there. So
the explanation, so the דרשה drasha is that it used to be
that you would let the judgment sleep over, and that would ensure
that it would be צדק, tzedek, that it would be a righteous
judgment because it would sleep, you would sleep on it. Now you
judge in the same day and you, the court, is turning into
murderers, as you're executing people without giving them due time and due
process and without sleeping a night. So you now are like you
are murderers. So you see you have to sleep on it, especially
if you're going to be taking somebody's life. ורבא אמר מהכא. V'Rava
amar mehacha. Rava says from here, אשרו חמוץ. Ashru chamotz. So the
verse is like, you know, defend the oppressed, but we're going to
read it the following way: אשרו דיין, Ashru dayan, praise the judge
שמחמיץ את דינו, she-machmitz et dino, that lets his judgment leaven, you
know, gives it time to percolate and so on. And that's where
he learns it. And now of course, praise doesn't mean it's required,
so you know, the earlier דרשה drasha is more powerful, calls them
a murderer if they don't do it. Anyway, ואידך, ve-idach, the other
one would say, what do you do with the פסוק אשרו חמוץ?
pasuk ashru chamotz? אשרו חמוץ ולא חומץ. Ashru chamotz velo chometz. Come
and defend the oppressed and not the oppressor, which basically means that
if somebody, like the way Tosafos says, it's hard to know the
exact parameters, but Tosafos says let's say somebody did personal injury to
someone, so he's coming to get justice, and the other person says,
well, the guy owes me a million dollars. So you first hear
the case of personal injury because that's the oppressed, and then you
go ahead and hear his claim that he's owed a lot of
money by the guy he beat up. Okay, ואידך האי מלאתי משפט
מאי עביד ליה? ve-idach hai meleiti mishpat mai avid lei? And the
one who learned it from אשרו חמוץ, ashru chamotz, what do you
do from the פסוק pasuk I used to be filled with justice?
כרבי אלעזר. K'Rabbi Elazar. Like רבי אלעזר אמר רבי יצחק. Rabbi Elazar
amar Rabbi Yitzchak. אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Elazar
amar Rabbi Yitzchak, כל תענית שמלינין בה את הצדקה, kol taanit she-malinin
bah et ha-tzedaka,
any fast day that they would let the charity sleep over, כאילו
שופך דמים, k'ilu shofech damim,
it's like you committed murder. So what Rashi explains it is on
a fast day that would start in the morning, so at night
people would be eating, and one of the things that they would
do, you know, fast day is about תשובה. teshuva. And therefore you
would get people to, you know, give צדקה, tzedaka, and we're going
to see in a minute that צדקה tzedaka is in the concrete
form of food that you would then give to the poor at
night. It wasn't the fast yet, it was the night time. And
therefore, so if you give צדקה, tzedaka, then you know you've done
what you're supposed to. מלאתי משפט. Meleiti mishpat. But if צדקה ילין
בה, tzedaka yalin bah, if you let the charity sleep over and
wait to give צדקה tzedaka until the next morning, then מרצחים, meratzchim,
it's like you killed the poor people because, you know, they're going
hungry and they're dependent on this food. שנאמר מלאתי משפט צדק ילין
בה. shene'emar meleiti mishpat tzedek yalin bah. והני מילי בריפתא ותמרי, V'hani
mili b'rifta v'tamri,
that's only things like bread and dates, which they are, you know,
is very satiating and that they can eat immediately. אבל בזוזי, Aval
b'zuzi, money, חיטי ושערי, chiti v'saari, and wheat
and barley, which is not readily edible, so in... In those cases,
if that's all you were you were collecting, לית לן בה, leit
lan bah, it's not as big of a deal, wait, letting it
sleep over, because it's not like you're depriving them of some immediate
substance. Okay. So anyway, that's where you know that you let the
judgment sleep over. לפיכך אין דנים, Lefikach ein danim, and therefore we
don't do it on ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, because we can't finish
it on שבת. Shabbos. So the בבלי Bavli is going to deal
with the issues the ירושלמי Yerushalmi didn't, which is why not just
take a day recess for שבת? Shabbos? So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
what's the reason? משום דלא אפשר, mishum delo efshar,
because you can't do it on ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. היכי לעביד,
Heichi l'avid, what do you want to do? נדייניה במעלי שבתא, Nedaynei
b'ma'alei Shabta, have the begin the case on Friday, ונגמריה לדיניה במעלי
שבתא, unigmarei l'dinei b'ma'alei Shabta, and finish it on Friday? That's okay
if you find him innocent, but דילמא חזו ליה לחובה, dilma chazu
lei l'chovah, maybe you'll find him a reason to say he's guilty,
ובעי למעבד הלנת דין, ubayei l'me'evad halanat din, and then you'll have
to like let the judgment sleep over, because if you find him
you want to find him guilty, you can't execute him the next
day. You have to wait another day and finish the judgment on
the following day. We learn that, that you have to let it
sleep, you have to sleep on it. So
where where were we? ובעי למעבד הלנת דין, ubayei l'me'evad halanat din,
you have to sleep on it and finish the judgment the next
day. So you can't finish the judgment on Friday. נדייניה במעלי שבתא
ונגמריה
בשבתא, Nedaynei b'ma'alei Shabta unigmarei b'Shabta, how about judging on Friday and
finishing the judgment on שבת? Shabbos? Now we all know you can't
execute on שבת, Shabbos, but well, excuse me, but first we're going
to suggest you execute on שבת. Shabbos. וליקטליה בשבתא, Ulikatlei b'Shabta, maybe
execute him on שבת? Shabbos? No, אין מיתה דוחה שבת. ein mitah
docha Shabbos. No, executing doesn't override שבת. Shabbos. We saw that discussed
in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, we'll see it discussed in the בבלי Bavli
in a minute. Now we're taking that for granted. Fine. So you
can't just immediately finish it on שבת. Shabbos. וליקטליה לאורתא, Ulikatlei l'orta,
okay, but why not do this? Finish the judgment on שבת Shabbos
and execute him Saturday night? נגד השמש בעינן, Neged hashemesh bayinan, no,
no, no. It says that the גמר דין gmar din has to
be by day and the execution has to be by day. So
you can't wait till Sunday morning, because that's עינוי הדין. inui hadin.
Well, we're going to say that. We haven't said that yet, excuse
me, I'm running ahead of myself. וליגמריה לדיניה בשבתא וליקטליה בחד בשבתא,
Unigmarei l'dinei b'Shabta ulikatlei b'chad b'Shabta, finish the judgment on שבת Shabbos
and execute him on Sunday. So no, נמצא אתה מענה את דינו,
nimtza atah me'aneh et dino,
you're anguishing his judgment. As long as the judgment isn't over, it's
not עינוי הדין, inui hadin, okay, because because he might he thinks
he might be found innocent. But once it was ruled that he
was guilty, very much different, you know, than in the States here,
you know, you have to go through a decade because of all
the appeals process, which is one way of going about it, which
is trying to save a life. But here, the גמרא'ס Gemara's sort
of approach is that once he's found guilty, you try to execute
him that same day. Otherwise, you're creating this long anguish of his
death sentence hanging over him. Okay, so you can't execute him Saturday
night because you have to execute in the day. You can't wait
till Sunday morning because if you go through the night, that's עינוי
הדין. inui hadin. You're you're waiting till the next day and you're
creating this anguish of ruling having the judgment against him and then
executing him. But then it finally asks the question that we've all
wanted to ask, which is: take a day recess. Start Friday, continue
Sunday. Okay, so it says ונדייניה במעלי שבתא ונגמריה בחד בשבתא, unedaynei
b'ma'alei Shabta unigmarei b'chad b'Shabta, why don't we start it on Friday
and continue it on Sunday and finish it on Sunday? No, מינשי
טעמיה, minshi ta'amei,
we're afraid
that they will forget their argument and their argument for the guy's
defense. So we do not want to go on recess in the
middle of a trial. אע"ג דשני סופרי הדיינין עומדים לפניהם וכותבין דברי
המזכין ודברי המחייבין, Af al gav dishnei sofrie hadayanin omdim lifneichem vechotvin
divrei hamazkin udivrei hamachayivin,
even though there's a court record of everything said everybody argued pro
and con. So how so what's the concern they'll forget? They'll just
reread the record. So the גמרא Gemara says no, נהי דבפומא כתבינן,
nehi d'befuma katvinan,
we write what they said with their mouth, we write the arguments
that they said, ליבא דאינשי אינשי, liba d'inshi inshi, but we don't
know what they were thinking. And there's a little play on words:
the heart of people, אינשי אינשי, inshi inshi, it's the same word
but it means you forget. People forget what they were thinking. So
we wrote down what they said, but if you take a break,
you're going to forget all of the arguments you had in your
head and all the nuance, and therefore we're afraid that that will
work out to hurt this person's interests and therefore we do not
go on a recess even for one day. Okay. הלכך לא אפשר,
Hilkach lo efshar,
therefore there's no way and we have to we cannot start it
on Friday. Now the גמרא Gemara gets to the thing we saw
in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, except it does it in a much longer
way, which is maybe you should make an argument that you could
execute on
שבת. Shabbos. אמר ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן, Amar lei Reish Lakish
l'Rabbi Yochanan, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, ותדחוס מת מצוה דחי
שבת מקל וחומר, V'tidchos met mitzvah dachi Shabbos mikal vachomer, why don't
let's say that if you have a מת מצוה, met mitzvah, a
body that nobody is burying and there's a מצוה mitzvah for everybody
to bury that person, let's say that such an important principle to
bury that you would even do it on שבת? Shabbos? Okay, where
should we make such an argument? So,
it says like this. Okay, and קל וחומר, kal vachomer, קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. ומה עבודה שדוחה שבת, uma avoda she'docha Shabbos, עבודה avoda
overrides שבת. Shabbos. Again, this is going to be transitive axiom of
inequality. עבודה avoda is greater than שבת. Shabbos. First מת מצוה דוחה
את העבודה, meis mitzvah docha es ha'avoda, but burying a מת מצוה,
meis mitzvah, that takes precedence even over עבודה. avoda. So the structure
of the argument is: עבודה avoda is greater than שבת, Shabbos, מת
מצוה meis mitzvah is greater than עבודה, avoda, takes precedence, so מת
מצוה meis mitzvah should be greater than שבת Shabbos and you should
do מת מצוה meis mitzvah on שבת. Shabbos. Now, where do you
see that מת מצוה meis mitzvah takes precedence over עבודה? avoda? ומאחותו,
mi'v'achoso, you learn it from the word of ומאחותו v'achoso by a
נזיר, nazir, that a נזיר nazir like a כהן גדול kohen gadol
does not become טמא tamei to immediate family members. But once it
says he can't become טמא tamei to immediate family members and it
says his father, why did it have to mention all of them?
לאביו ולאמו לאחיו ולאחותו. l'aviv u'l'imo l'achiv u'l'achoso. So the דרשה drasha
is each extra word there is telling you: this family member he
can't become טמא tamei to, but he can become טמא tamei to
a מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. Even if becoming טמא tamei to a
מת מצוה meis mitzvah not only violates his נזירות nezirus but would
go violate other things: he would be a נזיר nazir and a
כהן kohen and not only a כהן kohen but a כהן גדול
kohen gadol and not only a נזיר nazir and a כהן גדול
kohen gadol but somebody going to do a big מצוה. mitzvah. Nevertheless,
you know, his relatives he can't be מטמא mitamei to, but he
has to be מטמא mitamei to a מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. דתניא:
d'tanya: לאביו ולאמו לאחיו ולאחותו, l'aviv u'l'imo l'achiv u'l'achoso, מה תלמוד לומר?
mah talmud lomar? Why do you have to say all those words?
שהרי היה הולך לשחוט את פסחו ולמול את בנו, she'harei hayah holeich
lishchot es pishcho u'limol es bno, let's say this נזיר כהן גדול
nazir kohen gadol was also doing these two big מצוות, mitzvos, the
two positive מצוות mitzvos that you get כרת kareis for, they're so
important if you don't do them: ברית מילה bris milah and קרבן
פסח. korban pesach. So you would think all of those things should
say take care of that stuff and don't violate your קדושה kedusha
of כהן גדול, kohen gadol, of נזיר, nazir, prevent yourself from doing
these מצוות mitzvos just for the sake of a מת מצוה. meis
mitzvah. ושמע שמת לו מת, vishama she'meis lo meis, so if you
heard a relative, the guy heard a relative died, יכול יטמא, yachol
yitama,
maybe he should become טמא, tamei, תלמוד לומר... talmud lomar... לא יטמא.
lo yitama. No, for a relative you don't become טמא. tamei. But
יכול כשם שאינו מטמא לאחותו, yachol k'shem she'eino mitamei l'achoso, maybe the
same way he wouldn't do it for his sister, כך אינו מטמא
למת מצוה, kach eino mitamei l'meis mitzvah, he wouldn't be מטמא mitamei
for a מת מצוה? meis mitzvah? תלמוד לומר... talmud lomar... ולאחותו. u'l'achoso.
No,
the word is extra, it didn't have to say it, to tell
you לאחותו הוא דאינו מטמא, l'achoso hu d'eino mitamei, he's not מטמא
mitamei for his sister, אבל מטמא למת מצוה, aval mitamei l'meis mitzvah,
he would become טמא tamei for a מת מצוה meis mitzvah even
if it would mean violating his קדושה kedusha of כהונה kehuna and
כהן גדול kohen gadol and נזיר nazir and preventing him from doing
a פסח pesach and doing a ברית מילה. bris milah. Anyway, you
see therefore that מת מצוה meis mitzvah overrides עבודה. avoda. Here he's
a כהן, kohen, a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, he's going to be
טמא tamei and he's not going to do the עבודה avoda because
of this. So מת מצוה meis mitzvah is greater than עבודה, avoda,
עבודה avoda is greater than שבת, Shabbos, and again, as Joseph points
out, even if he's the only available כהן kohen and the עבודה
avoda really has to come to a stop, and therefore by a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, by a transitive axiom, מת מצוה meis mitzvah
should override שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so it says, where were we? So
למת מצוה. l'meis mitzvah. שבת שנדחית מפני עבודה, Shabbos she'nidchis mipnei avoda,
so if שבת Shabbos
is pushed away from עבודה, avoda, עבודה avoda is greater than שבת,
Shabbos, אינו דין שתהא מת מצוה דוחתה? eino din she't'hei meis mitzvah
dochatah? How much more so should מת מצוה meis mitzvah which is
greater than עבודה avoda push away שבת Shabbos and you should bury
do מת מצוה meis mitzvah on שבת. Shabbos. אמר ליה, amar lei,
so that's ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish question to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says back,
רציחה תוכיח. ritzicha tochiach. No, no, no, the counter-proof is, again, so
funny, at least in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it was called רציחת מצוה.
ritzichas mitzvah. Here it's just called רציחה, ritzicha, which we would translate
as murder, but it means execution. Execution will prove שדוחה עבודה, she'docheh
avoda, you execute a כהן kohen even if it means that the
עבודה avoda it overrides the עבודה, avoda, he won't be available to
do the עבודה, avoda, ואינה דוחה את השבת, v'eina dochah es ha'shabbos,
but you don't execute on שבת. Shabbos. So you see some types
of things can override the עבודה avoda like רציחה ritzicha and not
override שבת. Shabbos. And the same is true by מת מצוה, meis
mitzvah, it overrides the עבודה avoda but it doesn't override שבת. Shabbos.
Now, שדוחה עבודה ואינה דוחה את השבת. she'docheh avoda v'eina dochah es
ha'shabbos. So now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says back, and this is
where the ירושלמי Yerushalmi began, רציחה גופה תדחה את השבת מקל וחומר.
ritzicha gufah tidcheh es ha'shabbos mi'kal vachomer. Fine, let's execute people on
שבת Shabbos based on the same קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה עבודה
שדוחה שבת, uma avoda she'docha Shabbos, רציחה דוחה אותה, ritzicha docha osa,
if עבודה avoda is greater than שבת Shabbos because you do the
עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש Beis Ha'mikdash on שבת Shabbos and
nevertheless executing somebody is more important than the עבודה, avoda, שנאמר מעם
מזבחי תקחנו למות, she'ne'emar mei'im mizbachi tikachenu l'amus, so שבת שנדחית מפני
עבודה, Shabbos she'nidchis mipnei avoda, so שבת Shabbos which עבודה avoda overrides,
it's pushed away from עבודה, avoda, אינו דין שרציחה דוחה אותה? eino
din she'ritzicha docha osa? So if you execute and that takes precedence
over עבודה avoda and עבודה avoda takes precedence over שבת, Shabbos, execution
should take precedence over שבת Shabbos and you should execute on שבת.
Shabbos. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says: don't tell me it's a
counter-evidence, it's the same point. I'll say bury a מת מצוה meis
mitzvah on שבת Shabbos and execute somebody on שבת. Shabbos. So how
do you know not to do that? אמר רבא, amar Rava, so
רבא Rava says, כבר פסקה תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. kvar paska tana
d'bei Rabi Yishmael. You know, the תנא tana of the דבי רבי
ישמעאל d'bei Rabi Yishmael already learned out, you know, sort of cut
the rule, already learned out from a verse that you don't execute
on שבת Shabbos to go against your קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What's
the verse? דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל: d'tana d'bei Rabi Yishmael: לא תבערו
אש בכל משבתיכם, lo tiva'aru eish b'chol moshvoseichem, do not burn a
fire in all of your dwelling places. מה תלמוד לומר? mah talmud
lomar? What is this teaching you? So the גמרא Gemara interrupts: מה
תלמוד לומר? Mah talmud lomar? What's it teaching you? אי לרבי יוסי
ללאו יצאת, אי לרבי נתן לחלק יצאת. Ei l'Rabbi Yosi l'lav yatzat,
ei l'Rabbi Natan l'chaleik yatzat. It's telling you about the nature of
making a fire on שבת. Shabbos. There's a debate. If you make
a fire on שבת, Shabbos, according to one opinion, it's a negative
prohibition, but it's not death penalty, which is shocking. And that's why
the תורה Torah had a separate פסוק passuk of don't make a
fire to tell you it's not the death penalty, it's only an
independent prohibition. The other said, no, to tell you that each מלאכה
melacha is distinct. That's לחלק. l'chaleik. ללאו l'lav means only a negative
prohibition, not death penalty. לחלק l'chaleik means to make each מלאכה melacha
distinct. And for every separate מלאכה, melacha, if you do it בשוגג,
b'shogeg, you bring a separate קרבן. korban. So it makes one מלאכה
melacha distinct to say every מלאכה melacha is distinct. That's לחלק. l'chaleik.
Okay. תניא הבערה ללאו יצאת כדברי רבי יוסי. Tanya hav'arah l'lav yatzat
k'divrei Rabbi Yosi. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says making a fire is
was said special verse to tell you it's a simple negative prohibition.
רבי נתן אומר לחלק יצאת. Rabbi Natan omer l'chaleik yatzat. No, it's
to make it distinct, every מלאכה melacha is distinct. So that's why
you need the verse. No. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, fine,
that wasn't our question. תנא מושבות קשיא ליה. Tana moshvot kashya leh.
The question is why do you need the verse? You need the
verse to tell you this idea fire. But why did the verse
use the word in all your dwelling places? מושבות מה תלמוד לומר?
Moshvot mah talmud lomar? Why does it say your dwelling places? Now,
you don't have to tell me that שבת Shabbos applies everywhere. Of
course שבת Shabbos applies everywhere. מכדי, Michdy,
let's take a look. שבת חובת הגוף היא. Shabbos chovat haguf hi.
שבת Shabbos is a personal obligation. It's not related to agriculture. וחובת
הגוף נוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ. V'chovat haguf nohaget bein ba'aretz
bein b'chutz la'aretz. And obviously that applies everywhere, in the land and
out of the land. So מושבות דכתב רחמנא למה לי? moshvot d'katav
rachmana lamma li? Why did it have to say that don't make
a fire wherever you dwell? So משום דרבי ישמעאל אמר תלמיד אחד.
mishum d'Rabbi Yishmael amar talmid echad. So one תלמיד talmid said in
the name of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, לפי שנאמר, l'fi shene'emar, because
since the verse says כי יהיה באיש חטא משפט מות והומת, ki
yihyeh b'ish cheit mishpat mavet v'humat, if a person has a death
penalty he gets put to death, שומעני בין בחול בין בשבת, somei'ani
bein b'chol bein b'Shabbos, maybe you can execute somebody even on שבת.
Shabbos. ואני מקיים מחלליה מות יומת, V'ahamani m'kayem m'challeleha mot yumat, this
is exactly our question. Maybe you should execute on שבת. Shabbos. ואני
מקיים מחלליה מות יומת, V'ahamani m'kayem m'challeleha mot yumat, and what do
I learn from the verse which says that those who desecrate שבת
Shabbos are put to death? Which obviously you're not supposed to execute
on שבת. Shabbos. So בשאר מלאכות חוץ ממיטת בית דין. b'sh'ar melachot
chutz mimitat beit din. Alright, that's all other cases. But the same
way you do עבודה avodah on שבת, Shabbos, when a בית דין
beit din executes, maybe they do that on שבת Shabbos too. או
אינו אלא אפילו במיטת בית דין? O eino ela afilu b'mitat beit
din? Or maybe it's telling you no, a בית דין beit din
can't execute on שבת. Shabbos. ואני מקיים והומת? V'ahamani m'kayem v'humat? And
so what about your obligation to execute? בחול אבל לא בשבת. B'chol
aval lo b'Shabbos. That would be in the weekday but not on
שבת. Shabbos. או אינו אלא אפילו בשבת? O eino ela afilu b'Shabbos?
He keeps on going back and forth. Or on the other hand
maybe it should be on שבת. Shabbos. So how do I know,
do you execute on שבת Shabbos or not? Yes, of course normally
it's a prohibition, but maybe we make an exception like we make
an exception by the עבודה. avodah. So תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the
verse teaches, לא תבערו אש בכל מושבותיכם. lo tivaru eish bechol moshvoteichem.
Now what does that tell you about execution? ולהלן הוא אומר, U'lehalan
hu omer, and somewhere else it says והיו אלה לכם לחקת משפט
לדרתיכם בכל מושבותיכם. v'hayu eileh lachem l'chukat mishpat l'doroteichem bechol moshvoteichem. This
should be the law for your generations in all your dwelling places,
and this is talking about executing murderers. So מה מושבות האמור להלן
בית דין, mah moshvot amur l'halan beit din, the same way there
it's about a בית דין beit din and about executing, אף מושבות
האמור כאן בית דין. af moshvot amur kan beit din. Here when
it says fire, it means fire in the context of executing like
שרפה. sreifah. And therefore it's saying a בית דין beit din in
מושבותיכם moshvoteichem that's executing somebody you cannot do it on שבת. Shabbos.
Okay. So now what do we know? We know that you don't
execute on שבת, Shabbos, even though you have this קל וחומר. kal
v'chomer. In even though it overrides עבודה, avodah, it doesn't override שבת.
Shabbos. And that's the answer to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. That's how
we know you don't bury a מת מצוה meis mitzvah on שבת.
Shabbos. Because even though a מת מצוה meis mitzvah is stronger than
עבודה avodah and עבודה avodah is stronger than שבת, Shabbos, nevertheless by
comparison to this case of the court execution, you see that just
because it's stronger than עבודה avodah doesn't mean that you actually it
overrides שבת. Shabbos. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Now, before
we get to the next point in the גמרא, Gemara, I just
want to pause for a moment and read this very interesting תוספות
Tosfot about taking a כהן kohen away from the altar in order
to execute him. Look at the תוספות שנאמר מעם מזבחי. Tosfot shene'emar
me'im mizbechi. So it says, ואפילו אין שם כהן ראוי לעבודה אלא
זה ועבודה נדחית. va'afilu ein sham kohen ra'uy l'avodah ela zeh v'avodah
nidchit. Even if he's the only כהן, kohen, this is what I
was quoting before, you would take him away, which shows that executing
overrides עבודה. avodah. ואם תאמר, V'im tomar, the תוספות Tosfot says, wait
minute, דמשמע דרציחה דוחה עבודה, d'mashma d'retzicha doche avodah, the fact that
it overrides to execute him, לאו משום דרציחה דוחה עבודה. lav mishum
d'retzicha doche avodah. It's not the importance of executing that interrupts him
doing the עבודה. avodah. אלא משום דגברא לא חזי. Ela mishum d'gavreh
lo chazi. If he's a murderer, he is not fit for being
a כהן. kohen. So it's not because the need to execute interrupts
the עבודה. avodah. If he's deserving the death penalty, he is not
a valid כהן. kohen. כדאמרינן כהן שהרג את הנפש לא ישא כפיו.
K'de'amrinan kohen she'harag et hanefesh lo yisa kapav. A כהן kohen who
murdered cannot do, give the blessing with his hand. שנאמר ידיכם דמים
מלאו. Shene'emar yedeichem damim malei'u. Your hands are filled with blood. וכל
שכן עבודה. V'chol sheken avodah. If he can't do ברכת כהנים, birkat
kohanim, certainly he couldn't do the עבודה avodah on the altar itself.
So it's not the idea of executing interfere. It's that he's a
פסול pasul כהן. kohen. So very interesting answer. ויש לומר ד V'yesh
lomar d' על כרחך חזי, al karchach chazi, maybe actually no, a
כהן kohen who is a murderer really can do the עבודה. avodah.
דהלא מחל עבודה, dehalo mechal avodah, we never see anywhere that if
a כהן kohen who is a murderer does the עבודה avodah that
the עבודה avodah is invalid. The קרבן korban is פסול. pasul. No,
the קרבן korban would be כשר, kasher, he would not desecrate the
עבודה. avodah. נשיאת כפים חומרא בעלמא הוא שאר בידיה חומרא בעלמא הוא,
nesiat kapayim chumra b'alma hu sha'ar b'yadei chumra b'alma hu, and the
fact that he doesn't do ברכת כהנים, birchat kohanim, of course that
should be less important, less weighty, excuse me, than the עבודה, avodah,
but it's a חומרא, chumra, it's not that if he actually would
do, he really is כשר kasher to do the עבודה, avodah, to
do נשיאת כפים, nesiat kapayim, it doesn't invalidate it. And no so
and the fact that we don't do it for נשיאת כפים nesiat
kapayim is a חומרא. chumra. ועוד יש לומר, v'od yesh lomar, no,
maybe נשיאת כפים nesiat kapayim for this regard is weightier, maybe he
really is really פסול pasul for ברכת כהנים birchat kohanim and not
for the עבודה. avodah. ועוד יש לומר דשאני נשיאת כפים לפי שהיא
בידיו, v'od yesh lomar deshani nesiat kapayim lefi shehi b'yadav, he murdered
with his hands, the first: your hands are filled with blood, ואין
קטיגור נעשה סניגור, v'ein kategor na'aseh sanigor, the prosecuting attorney, the hands
that committed murder, cannot be the hands that bless. כדכתיב קרא בפרישכם
כפיכם אעלים עיני מכם, kedichtiv kra b'farishechem kapeichem a'alim einai mikem, you
reach out your hands, I'll cover my eyes. Of course, it's funny,
the עבודה avodah is also done with the hands, but it doesn't
emphasize the hand, right? The ברכת כהנים birchat kohanim is called נשיאת
כפים, nesiat kapayim, it's all focused on the raising of the hands,
and therefore maybe specifically פסול pasul for that. Okay, anyway, here we
have the answer why we know you don't execute on שבת. Shabbat.
Now we have one final challenge to this. So it says like
this: אמר אביי, amar Abaye, השתא דאמרת, hashta d'amarta, now that you
said, אין רציחה דוחה שבת, ein retzicha docha Shabbat, אין רציחה דוחה
עבודה מקל וחומר. ein retzicha docha avodah mikal v'chomer. Let's now go,
now that we've established you don't execute on שבת, Shabbat, let's now
go and argue, apply that back to the issue about executing to
interfere with the עבודה. avodah. If שבת Shabbat is stronger than execution,
and we know עבודה avodah is stronger than שבת, Shabbat, then עבודה
avodah should be stronger than execution, and you shouldn't interfere with the
עבודה avodah to execute. השתא דאמרת אין רציחה דוחה שבת, hashta d'amarta
ein retzicha docha Shabbat, if execution doesn't interfere with שבת, Shabbat, אין
רציחה דוחה עבודה מקל וחומר, ein retzicha docha avodah mikal v'chomer, it
shouldn't interfere with doing the עבודה avodah מקל וחומר. mikal v'chomer. ומה
שבת שנדחית מפני עבודה אין רציחה דוחה אותה, uma Shabbat shenidchit mipnei
avodah ein retzicha docha otah, שבת, Shabbat, which is weaker than עבודה,
avodah, and nevertheless execution doesn't interfere with שבת, Shabbat, עבודה שדוחה את
השבת, avodah shedocha et haShabbat, עבודה, avodah, which is weightier that overrides
שבת, Shabbat, אינו דין שלא תהא רציחה דוחה אותה? eino din shelo
tehei retzicha docha otah? So execution is less than שבת, Shabbat, שבת
Shabbat is greater than execution, עבודה avodah is greater than שבת, Shabbat,
so clearly עבודה avodah is greater than execution, and you shouldn't execute
and interfere with the עבודה. avodah. Nice קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Now
the problem is we have a פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says
you do interfere with the עבודה: avodah: מעם מזבחי תקחנו למות. me'im
mizbachi tikachenu lamut. אלא הא דכתיב מעם מזבחי תקחנו למות, ela ha
dechtiv me'im mizbachi tikachenu lamut, what about that פסוק? pasuk? ההוא בקרבן
יחיד דלא דחי שבת. hahu b'korban yachid d'lo dachi Shabbat. That means
you could take away the כהן kohen to execute him if it's
preventing him from bringing a private קרבן, korban, because a private קרבן
korban doesn't override שבת, Shabbat, a private קרבן korban is weak. But
if the כהן kohen is doing a public קרבן, korban, the עבודה
avodah of like a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, then that, that type
of עבודה avodah is weighty, it overrides שבת. Shabbat. So when that
weighty עבודה avodah that overrides שבת, Shabbat, you shouldn't execute a כהן
kohen and interfere with that עבודה, avodah, the same way you don't
interfere with שבת. Shabbat. That's a good argument. Okay, so we will
pick up with this tomorrow and we will, let's just finish it.
Okay, let's finish the, let's get the answer. Okay. So אמר רבא,
amar Rava, לא תהא רציחה דוחה קרבן יחיד מקל וחומר. lo tehei
retzicha docha korban yachid mikal v'chomer. No, I will tell you the
following. If you say that, that the פסוק pasuk will be left
to talk when the פסוק pasuk says executing doesn't interfere with עבודה,
avodah, you want to say well that we can say is talking
about when it's a personal קרבן. korban. רבא Rava says no, I'll
make you an, I can prove from a similar קל וחומר kal
v'chomer that once you're saying that עבודה avodah won't interfere with a
public קרבן, korban, עבודה avodah also shouldn't interfere with a personal קרבן.
korban. How do you know
that? מקל וחומר, mikal v'chomer, here's the קל וחומר: kal v'chomer: מה
יום טוב שנדחה מפני קרבן יחיד, ma Yom Tov shenidcha mipnei korban
yachid, you can bring your personal קרבן korban on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. So personal קרבן korban is greater than יום טוב. Yom Tov.
אין רציחה דוחה אותו, ein retzicha docha oto, but יום טוב Yom
Tov is greater than execution. If you don't execute on שבת, Shabbat,
the assumption is you don't execute on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
here's our קל וחומר: kal v'chomer: יום טוב Yom Tov is greater
than execution, private קרבן korban is greater than יום טוב, Yom Tov,
so private קרבן korban is greater than execution, and you won't interfere
with a private קרבן, korban, and then the פסוק pasuk isn't talking
about anything. So if you use those קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, you
won't interfere execution a private or a public קרבן. korban. So since
that can't be, it must be... it must be that actually you
do interfere, even a public קרבן. korban. Okay. קרבן יחיד korban yachid
שדוחה she'docheh את et יום טוב, Yom Tov, so a personal קרבן
korban which is bigger than overrides יום טוב Yom Tov is greater.
אינו דין שלא תהא רציחה דוחה אותו, Eino din shelo tehei retzicha
dochah oto, certainly execution shouldn't interfere with it, and therefore you'll, you'll
have nothing to do with the פסוק. pasuk. So now Rava says
wait, at least you could still have the פסוק pasuk talk about
a personal קרבן korban that if it according to one opinion. הניחא
למאן דאמר Hanicha leman de'amar אין נדרים ונדבות קרבים ביום טוב, ein
nedarim u'nedavot kreivin b'Yom Tov, according to the opinion that you don't
bring personal קרבנות korbanot on יום טוב, Yom Tov, then you're good.
You don't have a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Personal קרבן korban isn't
stronger than יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you could say execution doesn't
interfere with a public קרבן korban but does interfere with a personal,
because a personal קרבן korban is weak. It doesn't override יום טוב.
Yom Tov. אלא למאן דאמר נדרים ונדבות קרבים ביום טוב, Ella leman
de'amar nedarim u'nedavot kreivin b'Yom Tov, but if a personal קרבן korban
can be brought on יום טוב, Yom Tov, so מאי איכא למימר,
mai ika l'meimar, what can you say? Because now you can use
the same, you say, you say okay execution doesn't interfere with a
public קרבן korban and the verse that says you execute the כהן,
kohen, that's a private קרבן. korban. But Rava says I'll make you
a קל וחומר kal v'chomer that private, that even by a private
קרבן korban execution shouldn't interfere. Private קרבן korban is greater than יום
טוב, Yom Tov, יום טוב Yom Tov is greater than execution, so
private קרבן korban is greater than execution and the verse is left
talking with nothing. So must be when the verse says you execute
the כהן, kohen, it's talking regardless. Private, public, you always execute. That,
that is weightier than the עבודה. avoda. So אלא אמר רבא, Ella
amar Rava, rather Rava said, לא מבעיא למאן דאמר נדרים ונדבות קרבים
ביום טוב דלא מתקיים אם מזבחי כלל. Lo miba'aya leman de'amar nedarim
u'nedavot kreivin b'Yom Tov d'lo mitkayeim im mizbechi klal.
Goes without saying according to what I just said that if you
bring a private קרבן korban on יום טוב Yom Tov the verse
has to be talking, doesn't, you're not left with anything about the
verse, there's nothing that you would interfere, there's no עבודה avoda that
if you use your קל וחומרים kal v'chomers you would interfere with,
okay. So that proves that you have to put aside the קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. אלא אפילו למאן דאמר נדרים ונדבות אין קרבין ביום
טוב, Ella afilu leman de'amar nedarim u'nedavot ein kreivin b'Yom Tov, even
if you say you don't bring private קרבנות korbanot on יום טוב
Yom Tov and therefore in theory you could say that you don't
have a קל וחומר kal v'chomer by a private קרבן, korban, so
execution doesn't interfere with a public קרבן korban and it does interfere
with a private קרבן korban and that's the verse. So you'd have
a way of explaining the verse. Even in theory you'd have a
way of explaining the verse, still I'm going to tell you
that execution interferes even with a public קרבן. korban. How do you
know that? הכתיב Ha-ketiv the verse says מעם מזבחי. me'im mizbechi. מאי
מזבחי? Mai mizbechi? מזבחי המיוחד לי, Mizbechi ha-meyuchad li, meaning the one
that it's designated for, and the מזבח mizbeich is fundamentally designated, ומאי
ניהו תמיד. u'mai nihu tamid. The תמיד tamid is the primary thing
that you bring on the altar. So it says my altar, it
means the fundamental עבודה avoda that you do on the altar, which
is the public קרבן. korban. Even if the כהן kohen is doing
a public קרבן, korban, you interfere and you execute him. ואמר רחמנא
מעם מזבחי תקחנו למות. V'amar rachmana me'im mizbechi tikachenu lamut. So we
have this irony. Execution interferes with a כהן kohen doing the עבודה,
avoda, okay, but, and עבודה avoda is stronger than שבת, Shabbat, but
execution is not stronger than שבת. Shabbat. You don't execute on שבת,
Shabbat, you don't bury a מת מצוה meit mitzvah on שבת, Shabbat,
but you do do the עבודה avoda on שבת Shabbat and you
do have execution interfering with the עבודה avoda and taking the כהן
kohen away in order to execute him and not let him do
the עבודה. avoda. Okay, we will pick up with this tomorrow.